Guide to the Robert Byron Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1866, 1912-1941; Series II; 11.47; (28 boxes)
  - Writings of Others
    - Braaksma, M.H., Travel and Literature, 1938 (Box 43, Folder 670)
    - Burlington Fine Arts Club, "Catalogue of an Exhibition of the Art of Primitive Peoples", 1935 (Box 44, Folder 671)
    - Conolly, Violet, "The Industrialization of Persia," Reprinted from the Journal of the Royal Central Asian Society 22, 1935 July (Box 63, Folder 857)
    - Edwards, Margaret, letter to the editor regarding Byron's article on Wiltshire, 1933 (Box 63, Folder 858)
    - Handbook for South Africans Visiting London, 1936 (Box 44, Folder 672)
    - Howard, Ankaret. "Little Lemon: A Biographical Essay", 1928 15 April (Box 44, Folder 673)
    - Mannowsky, Professor. "The Uphagen House in Danzig" and "The Treasures of the Church of St. Mary's in Danzig", undated (Box 44, Folder 674)
    - Reitlinger, Gerald. "Medieval Antiquities West of Mosul", 1938 (Box 44, Folder 675)
    - Rothamsted Experimental Station, "Abridged Report", 1945 (Box 44, Folder 676)
    - Russell, Bertrand. "Political Ideals", undated (Box 44, Folder 677)
    - Stephanides, Th., "The Bridge of Arta", undated (Box 44, Folder 678)
    - "What Happened at Leeds", 1917 (Box 44, Folder 679)
    - Unidentified. "The Right Dishonourable David Lloyd George", undated (Box 44, Folder 680)
    - Empty folder (Box 45, Folder 681)
- Other Papers, 1923-1940, undated; Series III; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  The series is organized into two subseries: Associations and Personal Papers.
  The series contains material documenting Byron's involvement with the Federal Union Club and the Georgian Group as well as personal papers (such as bills, journals and notebooks, resume, and other material) recording his travels and personal life. Of particular interest is a scrapbook from Byron's schooldays at Eton and Merton College (Oxford) containing photographs, correspondence, newspaper clippings, invitations, visiting cards, and other ephemera.
  - Associations
    - Federal Union Club
      - Correspondence, writings, pamphlets, and membership leaflets, 1938-1941 (Box 63, Folder 859)
        Includes Byron's drafts of "The Principles of the Association," "Proposal For a Magazine on Britain," and BBC interview, as well as booklets "From Chaos to Order in International Politics" and "The Ending of Armageddon" by Lord Lothian
      - Agendas and Meeting Minutes, 1939-1940 (Box 63, Folder 860)
    - Georgian Group, 1937-1939 (Box 45, Folder 682-685)
      Includes meeting agendas, minutes, background materials, and drafts
  - Personal Papers
    Arranged by format.
    - Bills, 1934-1940 (Box 45, Folder 686-687)
    - Bills, 1934-1940 (Box 46, Folder 688-690)
    - Journals and Notebooks
      - Notebook with Byron's play "The Emperor's Wife", 1915 (Box 64, Folder 861)
      - Abberley Hall School, 1917-1918 (Box 64, Folder 862-864)
        Contains Byron's description of the scholarship examinations for Eton; observations on nature (a title page for the diary reads: "For Nature and Other Things of Interest"); list of pubs; various sketches; class notes
      - Eton College, 1919 (Box 64, Folder 865-867)
        Including notebook with Byron's essays with his teacher's comments
      - University of Oxford, circa 1923 (Box 64, Folder 868)
      - Italy, 1923 (Box 46, Folder 691-691a)
        Contains Byron's account of his trip to Europe with Lord Beauchamp and his sons Hugh Lygon and the future Viscount William Lygon Elmley
      - Greece, 1925 (Box 46, Folder 692-694)
      - Greece and Turkey, 1926 (Box 46a, Folder 694a-696a)
      - Spain, 1928 (Box 46a, Folder 697a-698a)
      - Russia, 1932 (Box 64, Folder 869)
      - Russia, 1935 (Box 46, Folder 695)
        Includes self-portrait dedicated to his family and signed from "Siberian Son"
      - Germany, 1936-1938 (Box 62, Folder 826-826a)
        General
        Accompanied by transcript typed in 2005.
      - England, After 1938 (Box 64, Folder 870)
        Typescript of Harold Nicolson's diary (September 19-28, 1938)
    - Diaries and Day Planners
      - 1926 (Box 64, Folder 871)
      - 1938 and 1940 (Box 64, Folder 872-873)
    - Scrapbook from Eton and Oxford, circa 1917-1926 (Box 64, Folder 874-875)
      Includes clippings of Byron's letters to the editor and articles (such as those from The Cherwell ), letter from Lytton Strachey regarding the "1840 Exhibition," and invitation and photographs from Viscount William Lygon Elmley's coming-of-age party.
    - Address books, undated (Box 65, Folder 876-877)
    - Passport, 1923 (Box 65, Folder 878)
    - Dinner menu signed by guests (largely friends from Oxford University), circa 1920s (Box 65, Folder 879)
    - Newspaper articles and other ephemera relating to friends and family, 1933-1937, undated (Box 46, Folder 696)
    - Curriculum Vitae, 1939 (Box 46, Folder 697)
    - Swan Walk apartment plan drawn by Byron, undated
    - Table plan for The Incorporated Association of Architects and Surveyors annual dinner, 1932 December (Box 46, Folder 697a)
- Drawings and Photographs, 1925-1931, undated; Series IV; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  The series is organized into two subseries: Drawings and Photographs.
  The series contains drawings and photographs created by Byron documenting his travels and personal relationships.
  - Drawings
    - Sketch of room at Oxford, circa 1925 (Box 65, Folder 880)
    - Sketchbooks (predominantly containing drawings of Italy), undated (Box 47, Folder 698-699)
    - Sketchbook from trip to Europe, 1924 (Box 65, Folder 881)
    - Sketchbook from trip to Lundy Island (England) with David Talbot Rice, 1925 (Box 65, Folder 882)
    - Drawings from travels including Athos, Persia, Afghanistan and other unidentified locations, undated
    - Drawings from travels including Athos, Persia, Afghanistan and other unidentified locations, undated (Box 65, Folder 883)
    - Profile portrait of a man, watercolor on paper (Series IV), undated (Box Bsd, folder 888)
      The drawing features a profile portrait of a man in a red (military?) jacket, and has as design elements a hammer, sickle, and a broken wheat sheaf in the upper left corner, and the letters DAB in the upper right corner. It measures 50 x 68 cm and is not signed or dated.
  - Photographs
    Arranged in rough chronological order
    - Byron, friends, and family, circa 1910-1941 (Box 47, Folder 700)
      Includes portraits of Cecil Clonmore, Michael Rosse, Brian Howard (inscribed to "Lord B") circa 1920s, Desmond Parsons circa 1930s
    - Photographs of paintings by Gwen John, undated (Box 47, Folder 701)
    - Greece, Athos, and Turkey, 1925-1927 (Box 47, Folder 702-708)
    - Greece, Athos, and Turkey, 1925-1927 (Box 47a, Folder 708a-708d)
    - "The Holy Mount Athos" photograph album, 1926 (Box 48, Folder 709)
    - Austria and Czechoslovakia, 1928 (Box 48, Folder 710)
    - Byzantine art, circa 1929 (Box 48, Folder 711)
    - Flight to India, 1929 (Box 48, Folder 712)
    - India (largely New Delhi), circa 1929 (Box 49, Folder 713-726)
    - Russia and Tibet, circa 1930-1931 (Box 50, Folder 727-737)
    - Damascus, 1933 (Box 50, Folder 738)
    - The Road to Oxiana including Afghanistan, Jerusalem, Palestine, Persia, and Syria, circa 1933-1934 (Box 51, Folder 739-754)
    - The Road to Oxiana including Afghanistan, Jerusalem, Palestine, Persia, and Syria, circa 1933-1934 (Box 52, Folder 755-768)
    - China, 1934 (Box 53, Folder 769)
    - England, undated (Box 53, Folder 770)
    - U.S.A., undated (Box 53, Folder 771)
    - Photographs from Byron's travels mounted for exhibition, undated (Box 53a, Folder 771a)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 53, Folder 772)
- Family Papers, 1904-2005; Series V; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  The series is organized into two subseries: Eton College and Other Papers.
  The series contains material relating to the Byron family generally as well as bills, report cards and other material documenting Robert Byron's education at Eton College that were retained by his parents.
  - Eton College
    - Report cards and related correspondence, 1919-1921 (Box 54, Folder 773-774)
    - Bills, 1919-1922 (Box 54, Folder 775-778)
    - List of students and other information, 1921-1922, 1976, 2005 (Box 54, Folder 779-780)
    - The Eton Candle (volume 1) and leaflet for the Eton Society of Arts, 1922 (Box 65, Folder 884)
  - Other Papers
    - Will of Cecil Edmund Byron, 1911 May 18 (Box 55, Folder 781)
    - Bills from Abberley Hall School and other schools, 1912-1927 (Box 66, Folder 885)
    - Material about Coulsdon Court, 1938, undated (Box 55, Folder 782)
    - Overton House bills and related papers, 1922-1940 (Box 55, Folder 783-785)
    - Ephemera, 1904-1948 (Box 55, Folder 786)
    - Papers of Lucy Byron Butler, 1926-1995 (Box 55, Folder 787-788)
      Includes catalogues for exhibitions on Byron at Wellington College and Eton College
    - Lucy Byron Butler's notebooks for Letters Home, 1991 (Box 66, Folder 886)
    - Reviews and material related to James Knox's biography of Byron, 2003 (Box 66, Folder 887)
- Oversize, 10.02; (6 boxes)
  - Birth of Western Painting (Series II) (Box Bsd, folder 789)
  - First Russia, Then Tibet, proofs, corrected (Series II), 1933, undated (Box 56 (Oversize), Folder 790)
  - First Russia, Then Tibet, galley proofs (Series II), 7 July 1933 (Box 56 (Oversize), Folder 791)
  - First Russia, Then Tibet, reviews (Series II), 1933 (Box 56 (Oversize), Folder 792)
  - Imperial Pilgrimage, notes and background material (Series II), 1936, undated (Box 56 (Oversize), Folder 793)
  - Innocence and Design, galley proofs, corrected (Series II), May 1935 (Box 57 (Oversize), Folder 794)
  - Road to Oxiana, galley proofs, corrected (Series II), circa 1937 (Box 57 (Oversize), Folder 795)
  - Shell Guide to Wiltshire, background material (Series II), 1934 (Box Bsd, folder 796)
  - "Between Tigris and Oxus", printed version, Country Life (Series II), 1 December 1934 (Box Bsd, folder 797)
  - "A Clerk's Apology", Printed version from The New Statesmen and Nation (Series II), 26 March 1938 (Box Bsd, folder 797)
  - "The Coming Inauguration of India's Capital: Great Architecture on an Imperial Scale at New Delhi", printed version, The Illustrated London News (Series II), 31 January 1931 (Box Bsd, folder 797)
  - "Drawings of Persia and Afghanistan", printed version from Walker's Monthly (Series II), December 1934 (Box Bsd, folder 797)
  - "Fascism in the Dodecanese", background material and notes (Series II), 1912-1926 (Box Bsd, folder 798)
  - "Future of the India Mail", printed version, The Daily Express (Series II), 18 September 1929 (Box Bsd, folder 799)
  - "How We Celebrate the Coronation", reviews (Series II), 1937 (Box Bsd, folder 799)
  - "Islamic Monuments: Architectural Glories of Persia", printed version, The Times (Series II), 28 September 1934 (Box Bsd, folder 799)
  - "Le Mosaïques de Ste-Sophie", printed version (Series II), 13 May 1932 (Box Bsd, folder 799)
  - "New Delhi" articles for Architectural Review, proof and printed versions (Series II), January 1931 (Box 58 (Oversize), Folder 800)
  - Empty Folder (Box 58 (Oversize), Folder 801)
  - "New Delhi" articles for Country Life, printed versions (Series II), 1931 (Box 58 (Oversize), Folder 802)
  - "New Delhi: The Viceroy's House", printed version, The Graphic (Series II), 24 January 1931 (Box 58 (Oversize), Folder 803)
  - "The Pleasures of Spain", published version, Vogue (Series II), 13 June 1938 (Box Bsd, folder 804)
  - "The Road to Thessaly: On Lord Byron's Track in Epirus", printed version from Country Life (Series II), 1931 (Box Bsd, folder 804)
  - Articles on Russia and Siberia, "New Russia", printed version (Series II), 18 March 1936 (Box Bsd, folder 804)
  - "Spring Time in Spain", printed version, Harper's Bazaar (Series II), February 1931 (Box Bsd, folder 804)
  - "Timurid Architecture", proofs (Series II), 1937 (Box Bsd, folder 805)
  - General research materials (Series II), 1916-1938 (Box Bsd, folder 806)
  - General research materials (Series II), 1916-1938 (Box Bsd, folder 806a)
  - Unidentified drafts and notes (Series II), undated (Box Bsd, folder 806a)
  - Book reviews (Series II), undated (Box Bsd, folder 806)
  - Letters to the editor (Series II), 1925-1939, undated (Box Bsd, folder 806)
  - Georgian Group (Series III), 1937-1939 (Box Bsd, folder 807)
  - Georgian Group (Series III), 1937-1939 (Box 59 (Oversize), Folder 808)
  - Newspaper articles about friends and family (Series III), 1933-1937 (Box 59 (Oversize), Folder 809)
  - Swan Walk apartment plan drawn by Byron (Series III), undated (Box 59 (Oversize), Folder 810)
  - Drawings from travels including Athos, Persia, Afghanistan and other unidentified locations (Series IV), undated (Box 60 (Oversize), Folder 811-819)
  - Photographs of friends and family (Series IV), undated (Box 61 (Oversize), Folder 820)
  - Photographs of India (largely New Delhi) (Series IV), circa 1929 (Box 61 (Oversize), Folder 821-822)
  - Photographs from travels in Russia and Tibet (Series IV), circa 1930-1931 (Box 61 (Oversize), Folder 823)
  - Papers of Lucy Byron Butler (Series V), 1926-1995 (Box 61 (Oversize), Folder 824)
- Restricted Fragile Material, 0.42; (1 box)
  Restricted Fragile Papers contains nitrate negatives and may be seen only with permission of the appropriate curator. Printouts from the Digital Library have been substituted in the main files for reference use.
  - Boxes 47-48, folders 702-709 (Box CS, Folder 827)
  - Box 49, folders 713-726 (Box CS, Folder 828-829)
  - Box 50, folders 727-737 (Box CS, Folder 830)
  - Boxes 51-52, folders 739-768 (Box CS, Folder 831-833)
  - Box 53, folder 772 (Box CS, Folder 834)
- Correspondence